[Music]
[Applause]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer or
/ software this is Robert for software
engineering radio I'm joined by Eric
Lubo Eric is the CTO of simple reach a
social event publishing platform prior
to simple reach Eric worked at Guardian
digital conductor dot-com and Sherman's
travel where he built an email system
with analytics to send over a hundred
million emails per month recently eric
has presented at Cassandra World Summit
the New York City CTO school and at
interrupt New York Eric welcome to
software engineering radio hi Robert
thanks so thanks for having me you're
welcome Eric today our can i will be
talking about polyglot persistence Eric
I have built database applications
before it's pretty straightforward you
pick a database either my sequel Oracle
or sequel server and you choose an
object relational mapping tool for
whatever platform you're on and then you
write your app and that's all there is
to it right yeah I mean when you're
building a small application you
definitely have to go with what works
you definitely should start with what
you know you know when we started out at
simple reach we were a group of folks
who thought would be useful
because it was built for larger it was
made to scale and we thought that we'd
be able to use what we knew with rails
and in the first iteration of what we
built we thought would work like that
and it did work pretty well
but it's one of those things that you
start with what you know and then when
you realize what you know may not be
sufficient to handle the scale that
you've gotten to which
by the way is a luxury problem then you
adjust accordingly would you agree that
it's no longer a given that an
application will have a single data
store no actually I I don't I don't
think that it's a given at all you know
it really just depends on what your
application is and what it's used for
and what your scale is going to be and
what your usage patterns are and as a
result you know you could have a single
data store and you might be able to do
everything you need to do with my sequel
and or Postgres and the internal caching
engines those work just fine so it
really just depends on what what your
applications for but if you need
something that's going to perform at
scale like I would be incredibly
surprised if you could do it with a
single with a single datastore Eric then
in your opinion is scale the primary
thing that's pushing applications to use
multiple data stores
I think it's usage patterns different
usage patterns within an application
certain data stores are made to service
different usage patterns better for
instance one of the best things about
Redis is that you can guarantee that
everything is memory maps all the time
because that's the way it works but with
you know Orchestra or even my
sequel the only things that are going to
be memory mapped are the things that
have been most recently used and are
still in the the cache which could
present a bit of a problem if you need
something quickly and you're not sure
whether or not it's going to be back in
a few milliseconds or a few hundred
milliseconds and that could always
affect the user experience whereas with
Redis you may not be able to have the
same query patterns but or memcache for
that matter may not be able to have the
same query patterns but you can pretty
much guarantee that whichever you're at
whatever you're asking for is going to
come back fairly quickly I think though
that even with a single datastore let's
say it's my sequel that if your
applications small enough then
everything will be served out of memory
so isn't it really some combination of
scale or latency that is pushing the
application away from a single data
store to multiple specialized stores
yeah it still is ultimately scale and
usage obviously there's no point in
putting you know a huge Redis server in
front of something that's got about 10
or 15 users because yeah my sequel will
be able to handle all of that but it
also depends may be those 10 or 15 users
are storing you know gigs of data per
session and you don't want to have to
ask my sequel to hold on to that in its
query cache or its key cached especially
if you're slicing and dicing those gigs
of data quite heavily so maybe you want
to put you know pre computed queries
into Redis and you have some
intermediary engine say hey let me check
the cache first before I go down to the
database so I think the Thema you're
getting that there is choosing the right
tool for the job and that maybe gives
you a different answer for different
different features of your application
hundred percent I mean that's a actually
when I when I give these presentations
these talks I always end up there's a
few slides that I invariably include
every time I'm summer for entertainment
value but they also convey the idea of
so for those people who know what home
improvement is that the show with you
know Tim the Toolman Taylor
you know he's always got the right tool
for the job and I got a picture of him
standing there saying the right tool for
the job because that's that's basically
what you're after there are a lot of
tools out there I mean you need to know
what your job is and and what the best
one to use is and you know what the job
is is typically about data size data
access data storage data consistency and
those are the questions those are just a
few of the questions from the data side
I mean there's you know anywhere from 50
to 50 there's 50 plus questions you have
to ask when you're starting to build
something out that becomes much
larger than your prototype or your MVP
Erica I'm not going to ask you to list
50 things but could you pick top five
questions that you'd be asking when
you're you're trying to make those
decisions sure when you are looking at
so I tend to put these things in a few
different categories I basically set it
as data technology financial and other
and if you got those other questions
those are typically things like am I do
I have any legal requirements no like
HIPAA Phipps
sarbanes-oxley PII requirements things
like that support if you need it you
know is there a community around it you
know the data questions are talking
about your query patterns your data
ingestion volume loading and unloading
of data backup style or your display
requirements the technology side maybe
more infrastructure related do things
need to be encrypted or compressed on
the file system what all tolerance DP'd
you know if their support for monitoring
in your language the language that you
and your team are most comfortable
developing in I mean then there's other
like just general financial questions
like you know is this gonna require a
lot of hardware do I need to come up
with a clowder and iron hybrid like do I
need to be all in the data center as a
result what if something goes wrong what
do I do is it gonna cost me for support
is it gonna gonna be able to do this or
the community I mean there's tons of
questions in those categories that
you're gonna have to ask yourself and
your team to make those decisions those
are just sort of the superficial ones
that need to you know that we found most
important to address but there's
certainly a lot more that I have listed
and have asked sure as you mentioned the
programming language would you say that
you start from programming language that
your team is comfortable with and then
you look for persistence stores that
have good drivers in that language or
are you
generally are the data requirements so
so much of a constraint that you need to
pick a data store and then maybe learn a
new language but to access that data
store effectively so that's a great
question because it's actually something
that we faced at simple region we had to
just make that decision so we we went
through and we knew that we were there
were certain requirements we needed to
make and the two that sort of fell into
what was what we were most interested in
whereas HBase and Cassandra and no for
to if if everyone would like we ended up
at Cassandra and we went to that a fair
portion of our stack was Ruby and node
well the Ruby driver was really just a
rapt Java driver at the time and there
the node driver was pretty tough to work
with so what we ended up doing was once
we figured out that Cassandra was the
data store that we needed to make use of
we started shifting parts of our stack
over into Python because there Pike
Python driver Picasa is excellent very
well written and very performant and the
node driver we knew we needed to access
the data store in node jf we ended up
having to roll our own know driver which
is actually now turned to be turned out
to be the standard in market because we
just happen to and I say we meaning the
organization but I can say I tell you I
did not have much to do with the writing
of it um we did a great job and we've
gotten a lot of help from the community
to make it better so there was a little
bit of you know having to roll our own
and reinventing the wheel it was
certainly the last resort but it was
done and it was necessary for us that
means that I should have given you three
options rather than choose the language
that has a driver or choose the data
store the third option is write your own
driver yeah we were not thrilled about
having to do that but once we found that
the access patterns that we needed to
take advantage of weren't available
in the node.js driver that Twitter had
written or the one that was hosted on
Google code which I'm not quite sure who
wrote we found that well this is one of
those few options where you kind of have
to do it yourself okay
well Eric you said data as one it is
your number one question when I asked
you about the differentiating factors
could you drill down into that a little
bit and talk about what are some
different access patterns and when you
see a certain access pattern what kind
of data storage solution would that
point you towards sure so it's actually
not as clear-cut as that although when I
was first getting into these questions
that's really what I thought it was
about was just the query patterns but it
actually turns out to be quite a bit
more than that all right so when we
first started asking questions about
what the proper usage patterns were we
thought that it really came down to
query patterns and the fact is that
that's important but it's not the
end-all be-all and we drilled it down
into a couple of subcategories and one
of them is certainly what are my query
patterns you know am I going to be
pulling in slices of data and a slice of
data may look like if I have so in
Cassandra if I have my if a row is
everything that happened for this hour
for a particular URL that means that
I've got all the pageviews all the
tweets all the Facebook actions etc etc
so can I slice out all those facebook
actions and then look at them
individually that would be a query
pattern and you can do that in various
data stores but Cassandra happens to be
very well-suited to just slicing out
anything that starts with the the word
Facebook you know and if you have it in
composite columns then it's good there
another thing that's very interesting
for a very interesting question asked is
what is your data input methodology are
you batch loading are you taking data in
at a high volume high velocity
does the data need to be aggregated as
it's coming in does the data need to be
immediately available everywhere on its
way in so like all these are questions
around ingestion and just basic input
stuff so you know you can answer those
with am i under the eventual consistency
requirement am i required to have
real-time data immediately available and
what are my ingestion points can I write
data anywhere for the Cassandra you can
write it anywhere the eventually
consistent thing makes it show up
immediately or makes it show up not
necessarily immediately but within
typically a pretty reasonable amount of
time and you because you are writing to
many servers you don't have to worry
about typically you don't have to worry
about overloading one server unless you
have a hotspot in which case you may
need to think about redesigning your
your schema another big question that
you need to look at is what you what are
your display requirements do the does
the display pattern require you to pull
data out immediately what does this what
does the query look like for those
displays is it aggregated is it raw all
those things lend itself to determining
the design panel for you know input
storage and analysis or for all three of
those things so that once you can answer
the question of what your display
requirements are going to look like in
some shape or form you can start to
narrow down which data stores will work
well for you so there's actually a lot
of questions that go into this again I'm
sort of scratching the surface but I
build that first version of an
application and is great for
building a first version of an
application because it's because it's no
sequel you can just build and iterate
and iterate and iterate and as you start
to see things develop you can say you
know what is going to be
absolutely fantastic for what I'm doing
I don't need to change anything or
endeavor
hey you know what I'll go is really
great for a portion of our system but
it's not going to be able to hold up for
everything we do we need to explore
other opportunities there are other
options and that's what we did and
that's how we ended up in the in the
polyglot persistence realm so Eric are
you recommending then to application
architects start with something that's
general purpose that will meet as many
of your needs that you can anticipate in
the immediate future and then gradually
swap out different pieces of the system
when your initial solution breaks yes
that's actually exactly what I'm saying
because if you get to the point where
you're where your solution is breaking
it means that you've either done
something horribly horribly wrong which
we've certainly done ourselves or it
means that you're growing and you know
growth and scale our luxury problems but
they are problems nonetheless so over
architecting and over engineering is
something that we as engineers love to
do we're like oh new toys shiny object
let's play yes it's not it's either you
know not something you know yet or it
may not be what you need so you got to
start with something you know start with
a very good multi-purpose tool get as
many ideas out of your head and into the
application as you're willing to build
for your MVP and see what what bricks
things start to slow down or need fixing
that's when you may need to explore
other options Eric I recall one
situation where I was trying to sell
manager on the idea that they needed a
specialized type of data store for
certain aspects of the system and the
answer I was getting was yes but then we
would have two databases and that was
stated like that was the killer argument
and I should just drop dead do you think
there is a bit of a cultural change that
organizations need to make if they have
been building systems and there's a
ironclad rule in your mind that you have
one data store so there's a few things
that I think need to be addressed in
that question absolutely I do agree that
there that there is a culture change
that's required but something that you
have to keep in mind is that the idea of
having a lot of data what the term big
data or having a lot of data means has
drastically changed over the past five
years with Amazon Web Services and
hardware getting cheaper and compute and
compute power getting cheaper and more
widely widely available the amount that
people can do with or what people can do
with it with a large amount of data is
becoming more and more and more so you
know whereas maybe a couple of years ago
maybe ten years ago if you wanted to do
something interesting with a census data
like you know odds are you wouldn't be
able to store that on your hard drive
now you may or may not be able to store
that on your hard drive but you could
certainly grab an instance in the cloud
and have a few terabytes across an EBS
set of EBS volumes store that and run
some interesting analyses on it yeah and
not you're from now be able to stir it
on your mobile phone exactly I mean
there is a there's a definitive change
in the availability of both storage and
compute and compute power that allows
for these things so that in and of
itself is a huge culture change so
people who are not willing to step in
with that culture change are certainly
not going to be willing to explore a new
idea of perhaps having multiple data
stores now the other reason in my
opinion that I said I've seen this
hesitancy around hesitation rather
around multiple data stores is that
there's certainly a requirement there's
a knowledge requirement around it I mean
if we have four data stores at simple
reach that means that at least one
person has to know how to work each of
those four data store
like ah if there's four people then one
of them has to be an expert in some way
shape or form in each one of them
because when something goes wrong
somebody has to know how to fix it so at
that point you're already with your
requirements for personnel goes up your
requirements for knowledge go up and
it's not that engineers aren't to the
task or willing but it's more there's a
lot more that has to go into it because
again there's so many only so many hours
in the day and then you're managing more
data stores you're managing more people
you're managing more machines and more
applications within that so you know
when you have multiple data stores and
you have potentially your data stored
across multiple data stores a natural
thing when most people come from our
DBMS is we'll say well if I have one
thing in one day to store and one thing
in the other why don't I join them well
that's you know that's a dangerous thing
that to do because now your intra data
store your inner data store joins are
very slow and they're cumbersome and you
have to figure out new ways to access
your data which means new paradigms
within applications so you're
essentially looking for a culture change
in institutional knowledge you're
looking for a culture change in
availability of data and applications
you're looking for a culture change in
in usage patterns and all these things
are very scary to a manager who's got a
budget sure see you're going to
something out that I find really
interesting which is from a system
architecture perspective how do you know
when you've got the right overall
balance of optimality for each feature
versus managing the complexity and the
cost of the entire project and if each
developer or each team is looking at
what is optimal for their problem they
might arrive at a particular data store
that's ideal for what they're doing but
how does from a project perspective you
make this trade-off between the growth
and complexity and cost of the entire
system against
doing something better or maybe just
living with the fact that you're gonna
do something not as well
yeah that's that's tough it's certainly
tough in you know larger organizations
who may not be as flexible one of the
beautiful things about being in a
start-up is that if something's not
working you have the option generally
speaking to ditch it and try something
else
so it's really hard to gauge you know
from the big company perspective when
it's okay to dip something and try again
how much like you have to support
because in a start-up typically you're
not going to be supporting a whole lot
of legacy legacy problems or legacy data
stores or applications so it's a very
different set of requirements typically
that you're entering into this decision
within a smaller organization than with
a with a larger organization but they're
all things that you have to keep in mind
sure I I remember seeing a talk by
somebody who was explaining why they
decided to build a messaging system on
my sequel so they could take a custom
messaging system out of production
because they wanted to reduce the load
on their ops guys from having to manage
additional pieces of middleware and they
felt like that was the right decision
for them to have one less infrastructure
piece rather than one more yeah that to
me that that that just sounds scary it's
good to be quite frank because you're re
architecting something that you're
reinventing the wheel when odds are
there's something that's already there
to do a job to do that particular job I
mean the amount of messaging systems
that are out there that use more
high-performance systems than my sequel
you know there's a ton of them ActiveMQ
RabbitMQ bitly just built their own @sq
and built Lee bit Lee has done a
phenomenal job of releasing tools and
building their own tools in in-house
which is typically something that you
don't see done a lot but between like
nsq and des blooms like they've
bittley's done an excellent job so while
that's generally a scary thought to
reaaargh attacked it's uh you know
sometimes can be useful yeah that's what
gets into the build versus by arguing
sure um we're by I guess in this term is
you know use open source available tools
but does typically get into the build
versus buy yeah now I would like to
double a bit into another big
architectural pattern that's gonna come
up when you're building this type of
system do you recommend an application
this code directly against a driver for
each data store or would you put an
abstraction layer around let's say
real-time analytics aggregates whatever
your core abstractions are and then give
yourself the ability to swap in or swap
out different persistent stores based on
without without having having to to
re-architect or recode your applications
sure so again I'll address this in the
through the lens of simple reach because
of what we did what we ended up doing
was we built a service architecture so
anything that does any reading of data
whatsoever it hits our internal API and
our internal API is essentially a
service architecture
it speaks JSON because every language
has you know json bindings in some way
shape or form they're all pretty pretty
fast and any read query it just hits the
api and the api says you know what i
know which data store i need to get this
data from i know how to make it look the
the internal architecture is written in
I'm sorry the internal service
architecture is written in nodejs
so if it needs to go out to multiple
data stores at the same time and fire
off a bunch of threads you know hit
Cassandra
I hate Redis and and comeback I
think there was one single JSON response
back to the back to the requester or
whatever the the requesting agent is
what we found though is that that does
not typically apply as well for writes
um it does slow down writes quite
heavily so we actually haven't solved
that problem yet so we tend to write
things directly to the datastore not
going through that service architecture
but for reads it has made a huge dent in
in you know solving the speed problems
that comes with having this multiple
data source so the architecture itself
having the internal service architecture
lends itself very well to being able to
plug-and-play a great example of what
this did for us is when we were trying
to find the proper analytics package to
help us get off the ground and we were
trying to decide info bright and
infinity be there both my sequel store
column storage engines and so they and
they both work with the my sequel driver
they both talked they both speak my
sequel so what we did was we put both of
them we spun up one machine for each one
for info bright one for infinity B and
then every request that was supposed to
go there went to both machines
simultaneously they were both timed and
you you know for consistency's sake you
always want to read from one machine so
in case the data gets a little bit out
of sync the client doesn't end up seeing
some weirdness but we sent both queries
to both we used all of our all of our
responses were from infinity B then we
take the hashed version of the query
store that in along with the
response times and we just built up this
huge response time database a collection
rather in of the query and how
long it took to respond the query and
how long it took to respond we took a
look at the graphs and we found that
certain queries performed much faster
certain query on
on one type certain queries perform much
slower we ended up making our decision
we went with info bright for a variety
of reasons we ripped infinity be out and
there was absolutely no downtime because
all we had to do was just point just say
to the service architecture from now on
go with the info bright responses and
there was that's a great story Eric
probably better to been able to do that
on the live system in production than
trying to set up on a test network and
benchmark them against test data yeah
yeah and then once we realize that you
know hey we can't just have one server
because anybody who's ever built a
fault-tolerant system knows that a
single point of failure is always the
point that's going to fail we built we
added a new we added a second machine so
now we have two identical info bread
machines and they both load the data
simultaneously they and and we just
built into the service architecture if
you go to your primary info bread
machine and it stopped responding go ask
the other one when when we needed to add
the second info Brite machine for for
redundancy we just set it up so that
both info Brite machines would continue
to load all the data regularly and with
no time whatsoever we added the second
machine in and the rolling restart
across the service architecture the
internal API allowed us to just say any
query that comes in go immediately to
the first info breaks or info break
server and if that's down don't ask the
other one so I'd like to shift a little
bit to another topic something I've seen
can be very disruptive in these systems
with multiple data stores and multiple
programming languages is I guess I would
call it schema evolution or data model
evolution
now instead of your data tables and your
objects you've got times n how how do
you manage that process in without how
do you manage that process efficiently
are you talking about just determining
what the best schema is for the data or
now you've got version 1 of your
application requirements change or you
build a new feature now you have to
modify the schema but it's not just in
one place it's in five places and it's
in three different programming libraries
right so that's what's that's what's
good and bad about that service
architecture because the read pattern
never has to change the only thing that
needs to know about that read pattern is
the service architecture anything that's
requesting the data just says yep just
continue giving me the data and then you
build a map inside of that service
architecture to say this is what it
looks like now this is what it used to
look like for this request so you know
there
theoretically you could hit a point in
which those Maps become a pain in the
butt to deal with there's too many of
them we haven't hit that point yet you
know knock on wood but it certainly is
certainly plausible for that to happen
on the right side on the other hand we
actually haven't run into that yet and
we've we've come across a couple of
different ways that we've had to read
the data but in terms of writing the
data the only thing that we've had to do
is write it in additional formats and we
haven't had to redo one of the format's
that we're writing with so that hasn't
really been that much of a big deal for
you it's simpler each correct
scuse me the reason that we've had to
redo some of the way we write the data
I'm sorry add some of the ways we write
the data is because are the features
that we made that we're developing have
different display requirements so it's
faster to query data that looks like X
then looks like Y for a certain feature
so because storage is cheap it's just
easier for us to
right the data and make it look a
different way so we may have the data
stored four times this piece of data
stored for x now we store it a fifth
time but it makes this feature that
we're developing much faster to develop
and very easy to use and implement so
it's it's worth it I would think in this
type of architecture that it puts even
more importance on overall system
testing because everyone could test
their own little piece of code that
writes to one data store but that
doesn't mean that the entire system will
behave correctly because you have
greater possibility of consistency
problems that is there anything through
that yes
consistency across data stores is a huge
problem for us there was a huge problem
for us rather and you know the way we
solved it was we we have our front end
application and then we have an entirely
separate back-end application an admin
section so to speak I mean and when this
management or admin section is used most
frequently or where it's used most
frequently is we have built many screens
that look across the data stores at
certain types of data and say does this
look the same in each of the data stores
where it's supposed to look the same so
we have programmatic checks and then we
have visual checks in case we're unsure
about the programmatic checks you know
that was a lesson that we learned the
hard way by seeing you know in one day
to store this thing as ten tweets and in
another data store this thing is 14 and
we're like okay what happened there and
in order to figure that out we started
building for informatics X and we're
like okay programmatically it looks like
it should've worked
what happened then we go and make the
visual checks and we're like oh okay
so we started building screens in our
management section to compare data
stores and and responses from the
service architecture to to make sure
that we were getting back what we
thought we were getting back and to make
sure we were writing what we thought we
were writing did you
find it difficult to track down where
things were going wrong at first there
was difficulty because we were sort of
fudging our way through the process you
know that's that's a bit of a logic
issue in a lot of cases but as we got
more adept at you know the the patterns
of moving data around from one engine to
the other serve realize that there's
there's a good way to do this and a bad
way to do this and and it's a set of
best practices that really didn't exist
we were sort of fudge ETL processes and
we figured out that you know one we
should be documenting how we do this so
when somebody else comes along and do
something similar their fudging their
way through and trying to figure out
best practices as well and as much as
it's unpleasant sometimes to test and
write tests when you're trying to
iterate quickly in a start-up in this
sort of situation it's useful if you're
is your system structure in such a way
that all of your business critical data
has a single master copy somewhere and
if you lost all your data stores but one
you could regenerate everything from
master or do you have multiple
distributed master copies of different
pieces of data depending on where that
data lives again great question this was
something that we didn't really consider
up front but we came along after a while
and said you know what there has to be
an authoritative data source so
everything needs to be able to be
rebuilt from this and then we decided
that that was Cassandra so everything
that we do first gets put into Cassandra
and then gets shifted elsewhere there
might be other simultaneous things going
on like as we write a raw event to
Cassandra we may do a couple of
increments in and and
you know sets or increments in Redis as
well but I there is always going to be
in action in Cassandra so that means
that not only is that distributed and
not only is that fault tolerant but it's
also the one and only place that we have
everything and the reason that we chose
that is because we have nodes across
many availability zones so if Amazon
were to lose all of us east 1a we'll
still have a couple of copies of our
data in one B and one A and one C and if
we lose if Amazon were to lose one a and
1e we still have one B in one city we
can regenerate the machines in order to
we can regenerate the data on the other
different stores from those machines now
that except we have our entire
architecture spread out ility zone so
you know we have has the concept
of replica sets and shards so every
shard that we have has at least two
replicas in two availability zones for
my sequel we have one and one
availability zone in our secondary and
another availability zone so if Amazon
took a really really nasty hit and lost
to availability zones well then we would
have a problem as well as a whole lot of
other people so that's not really an
eventualities that we're concerned about
but we've done what we can to protect
ourselves again it wasn't that bad to
what extent then was the choice of which
technology would serve as a master
driven by the way that datastore handled
the multi data center distribution
almost entirely actually when we were
when we were coming to the conclusion we
were coming in the consensus internally
what what really would be an acceptable
authoritative data source we really said
okay there's two things that this
authoritative store needs to be able to
do one be distributed it has to be
distributed
and be able to survive you know partial
failures outages no losses whatever it
is and in our case we considered to be
that partial outage would be losing an
entire data center
I'm sorry losing an entire availability
zone the other part of it was because
whatever is going to be authoritative is
going to have a high volume of data
ingestion and a high velocity of data
ingestion it needs to be able to handle
all that and then distribute it without
slowing anything down so you know right
now as we're still in our growing stages
we're looking at a few hundred million
events per day social events per day
we're looking at a few over a few
million URLs and that translates to you
know a couple thousand of events per
second you have to ingest store and
manage so that me meant that you know we
had to figure out he the most fault
tolerant and be able to store all the
data coming in at a high velocity and a
high volume and wouldn't slow down any
of the read patterns so you know we
looked at and said hey is
working well for us but it's not been
our experience that we can do all this
writes all these rights to it and not
slow down the reads so what we ended up
doing was saying okay if we look at what
Cassandra does and how it does it we can
do high volume high velocity ingestion
and we could write to any node and we
can lose those notes fairly quickly and
still have that data elsewhere it's
actually for us actually came down to
not only the fault tolerance and the
distributed nature but also but also the
ability to hold on to and ingest data
very quickly and that you have some kind
of piece of your system where you could
starting from your master copy
repopulate everything else from zero if
necessary yes it would be extremely
artists very tedious and
it would take a while and writing those
MapReduce jobs is not goat would not be
very pleasant but it could certainly be
done if it needed to be done so you
mentioned earlier I want to come back to
the notion that Big Data the idea of
what that means has changed a lot in
recent years where did these so-called
Big Data technologies like Hadoop and
HDFS and the other platforms built on
top of that where do they fit in to the
picture well you know there was a
there's a very interesting question that
was posed when I was at the the New York
City CTO meetup and and somebody said
well what does big data' mean to you and
do you like to me I'm not a huge fan of
the term big data in general because big
is a very subjective term you know
what's big data to simple reach is
clearly not big data to Google you know
or Facebook so if we both aspire self
data companies you know in essence we
both do the meaning becomes slightly
skewed so to me being a data company in
general means that you're working with a
significant amount of data now again
significant could mean whatever it is to
you maybe it's the size of a spreadsheet
you know something just slightly bigger
than will fit in an Excel spreadsheet or
or maybe it's something else maybe it's
something once you hit one terabyte
maybe it's once you had a hundred
terabyte once you had a pet it's got
different the different meanings to
different people so when you look at the
evolution of these products and their
distribution a few years ago most
companies couldn't use these as I said
earlier because there was no way to
deploy these without a fair amount of
money you know being able to store 10 15
terabytes of data you know required a
fairly sizable investment and that was
not common there was not a whole lot of
data center knowledge to support that in
a district you know distributed through
the masses like there is now
so as tools started growing the you know
compute power and
the storage because the compute power
became more available in the store it
became cheaper then people started
getting into these these engines like
Hadoop and like map all the MapReduce
frameworks and and they're all now
they're coming up around it like data
stacks is is doing a lot with Cassandra
and being able to run Hadoop on on CFS
I'm using hive and pig and things like
that and there's even Google is sort of
publishing their papers and help helping
along technologies like like Dremel I
believe it's called which is their you
know wrote sequel query like engine
which is now being picked up by the
Apache foundation so these all these
things that are coming down the pipe are
just making the processing of data more
to the end user and in this case the end
user is typically businesses and
organizations who are you know coming up
through the ranks
Eric earlier you talked about a big
decision you made between HBase and
Cassandra could you walk us through what
how that process went if we needed to
take advantage of some sort of MapReduce
technology because we knew that the the
way our data was going to be stored in
the amount of data that we were going to
be looking at was was going to require
this but we didn't really know what the
right direction was so we started taking
a look at HBase we started looking at
Cassandra and and you know we looked at
a couple of others including Rioch you
know there's there's a ton out there we
looked at dynamo DB and EMR elastic
MapReduce and we really came down to a
few things first we pretty quickly ruled
out react at the time because it was
just the the tools were just a little
too immature and that's you know I don't
believe that's the case anymore but at
the time we were looking that was the
case we all pretty quickly ruled out
using dynamo DB on Amazon and Google App
Engine because the prop
that we saw was that you could very
easily code yourself into a corner if
all you need to start doing things with
your database so if all you start
needing to do things with your data
that's not under the basic storage and
query patterns of App Engine or DynamoDB
then you have to wait until Amazon or
Google comes out with a new release and
hope that what's what they're releasing
will help you with what you're doing and
if not then you have to figure out a way
to get all of your data out and if you
have terabytes of data that could be you
know a very problematic endeavor so that
sort of left us with HBase and Cassandra
and when we looked you know we did talk
to cloud era about HBase and we talked
to data about Cassandra and you know
there were a bunch of factors that we
were considering but you know the
biggest one that led us down the road of
Cassandra was the fact that we had an
influence in the roadmap at the time and
again cloud era has done a great job
since then of changing this at the time
the roadmap for Hadoop as it related to
HBase was very nebulous there wasn't a
clear like this is the people these are
the people who were in charge and these
are the people who are pushing HBase and
development forward and cloud era was
trying to get their foot in there and
since then have done a fantastic job of
of really pushing HBase forward but at
the time it just wasn't there and you
know speaking to the folks of data
stacks and being able to become a part
of the community and it is integral part
of the community and drive the roadmap
in the way we have and it's not just us
they do it for everyone
which is another great thing about them
that really gave us the comfort level -
comfort level with our decision and
being able to talk consistently about
the roadmap and perhaps injecting what
our use cases are and how the features
could be helpful to our use case because
odds are only one with a particular use
case we just might be the ones who are
most vocal about it at the time so
ultimately you know the deciding factor
was hey we can do pretty much the same
thing with HBase as we could do with
Cassandra
but having somebody be attentive to the
roadmap needs and where we were heading
that was probably the deciding factor
for the major deciding factor for us
Eric
if people would like to learn more about
you and follow your ideas how can they
do that there's a couple of ways to
follow me first I have a blog which I
don't keep updated as regularly as I'd
like to but I have a couple of posts in
the pipeline for the next few weeks at
Eric liubao org you can also follow me
on twitter at a loop out elu bo w those
are probably the easiest things to do I
also do speaking engagements here and
there I will be speaking at Boston
on October 24th if you're in the Boston
area great and if listeners would like
to learn about simple reach how can they
do that yeah you know generally simple
reach get content creators the ability
to see how well their content socially
so if you create content if you you know
published articles or videos or anything
along those lines
we can help you so if you head on over
to WWE and sign up for our public beta
which is where we're at at the moment we
can certainly help you see how well your
how your content is doing Eric thank you
very much for speaking to software
engineering radio thank you very much
for having me Robert
[Music]
thanks for listening to s-see radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at se -
radio net to support us you can
advertise su Radio by clicking the de
crédit delicious or slash buttons on the
site or by talking about us on Facebook
Twitter or your own blog if you have
feedback specific to an episode please
use the commenting feature on the site
so that other listeners can respond to
your comments as well this and all of
the episodes of se radio is licensed
under the creative commons
two-point-five license please see the
website for details thanks again for
your support
[Music]
[Applause]